{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One general in this war was so successful at Civetot and Xerigordon that he ignored it to fight the Danishmends. While ostensibly fighting in this war, Emicho of Flonheim massacred Jews. Kilij Arslan lost the Battle of Dorylaeum during this war, and the counties of Tripoli and Edessa were founded in its wake. This conflict was originally intended to aid Alexius Comnenus, and it began after cries of “Deus Vult!” at the Council of Clermont. For ten points, name this crusade which resulted in the 1099 capture of Jerusalem.",
      "answer": [
        "First Crusade or Prince’s Crusade",
        "People’s Crusade until “Emicho” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The policies of this period were supported by Ludvik Svoboda. To protest the end of this event, Jan Palach committed self-immolation. This event ended with the “Normalization” period under Gustav Husak,andithadbegunaftertheousterofAntoninNovotny.Theinitiatorofthisperiod,whopromulgated an “Action Plan” and “socialism with a human face,” was Alexander Dubcek. Soon after Leonid Brezhnev sent Warsaw Pact troops to quell it, he formulated his namesake Doctrine. For ten points, name this 1968 period of liberalization in Czechoslovakia.",
      "answer": [
        "Prague Spring or Prazske jaro",
        "Prazska jar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The name of this publication’s founder, Walter Bagehot [BADGE-ut] is used as a pen name for one of its editorial columnists. This publication’s name refers to an archaic name for support of free trade, as it was founded in opposition to the Corn Laws. Henry Kissinger once facetiously said that he no longer needs to think; instead, he just reads this London-based periodical. For ten points, name this weekly news magazine which provides commentary and analysis on current events, business, and politics, as well as a namesake branch of social science.",
      "answer": "The Economist"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler translated some of the couplets in The Knight in the Panther’s Skin, which was the national epic of his home country. A poem about this ruler mentions his “thick fingers” that are bulky and “fat like live-baits” as well as his wide “Ossetian torso.” His secret police ordered the execution of Osip Mandelstam for writing a satirical epigram. Nicholas Rubashov is supposedly unloyal to this man, called Number One, in Arthur Koestler’s Darkness at Noon. For ten points, name this totalitarian dictator of the USSR who died in 1953.",
      "answer": "Joseph Stalin or Joseph Dzhugashvili"
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting protesting one form of this activity depicted it in a blue circle near the top; in that work by James Ensor, a bird bleeds on a man’s head. In another work, two men watch this activity while standing against a red backdrop, while a woman turning away from this activity covers her eyes with gnarled fingers. Instead of watching this activity, two men in front of the artist’s signature, one holding a sheet of paper, look directly at the viewer. For ten points, name this activity performed in Rembrandt’s The Anatomy Lesson by Dr. Nicolaes Tulp.",
      "answer": [
        "dissection",
        "surgery",
        "vivisection",
        "The Vile Vivisectors"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, the elderly civilian Judith Henry was targeted by artillery, and Edward Porter Alexander utilized “wig-wag signalling” to tell Nathaniel “Shanks” Evans of an impending flank. This battle began after westward movement from Centreville resulted in skirmishing at Matthews Hill, and was decided when Joseph Johnston’s reinforcements arrived via railcars. Picnickers were horrified by Irwin McDowell’s defeat at, for ten points, what early victory for P.G.T. Beauregard, the first major battle of the Civil War?",
      "answer": "First Battle of Bull Run or First Manassas"
    },
    {
      "question": "Robert LaFollete’s suspicions regarding this event intensified after his Senate office room was raided. Following this event, Congress was granted the power to compel testimony by the Supreme Court’s ruling in McGrain v. Daughterty. The perpetrators of this event took advantage of the Mineral Leasing Act. Edward Doheny acquired Elk Hills in this event, which led to the downfalls of Henry Sinclair and Albert Fall. Bribes for favorable leases of federal land were given out in, for ten points, what scandal that rocked the administration of Warren G. Harding?",
      "answer": "Teapot Dome Scandal"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Crescentii helped one person with this name gain power upon the ascension of Otto II. Another person with this name issued Etsi du statu upon receiving an embargo for writing Clericos Laicos. An Anglo-Saxon who took this name felled Donar’s Oak, and a pope of this name declared that the church wielded two swords in Unam Sanctum. For ten points, give this name for a pope who fought with Philip IV and a saint who converted many in early 8th century Frisia and Germany.",
      "answer": [
        "Boniface",
        "Franco until “Etsi” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, a Nightstawker helicopter entered a vortex ring state and damaged its tail rotor. Some participants in this event claimed they used “cakebread” or “crankshaft” as a codeword instead of the controversial “Geronimo.” Contradictory accounts have emerged about whether or not the central figure in this event used women as human shields in his compound in Abbottabad. For ten points, name this May 2011 operation by Seal Team 6, codenamed Neptune Spear, in which the founder of Al-Qaeda was killed.",
      "answer": [
        "the death or killing, etc. of Osama bin Laden",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1892, Isaac Bruce was falsely convicted of rape in this state but saved from hanging by governor James Hogg. After the murder of Lucy Fryer in this state, the accused supposedly pled guilty during a one-hour-long trial attended by 10,000 people; after four minutes of jury deliberation, the lynch mob castrated, burned, and desecrated of the body of Jesse Washington, an act later labeled a “Horror.” The aforementioned Bruce case stemmed from an incident during the Juneteenth holiday, which commemorates this state’s 1865 abolishment of slavery. For ten points, name this state, the site of the 1916 Waco Horror.",
      "answer": "Texas"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler sent a punitive expedition against the Singhasari Kingdom on the island of Java. Though he managed to establish suzerainty over the Kingdom of Pagan, he was repulsed at the Battle of Bach Dang by Tran Hung Dao. After the death of his older brother, this ruler waged a destructive civil war against his youngest brother Ariq Boke in the Toluid Civil War. The remnants of the Southern Song Dynasty were defeated by this man at the Battle of Yamen. The capital of Xanadu was owned by, for ten points, what founder of the Yuan Dynasty, a prominent Mongol emperor?",
        "answer": "Kublai Khan or Yuan Shizu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kublai Khan, like other Mongol leaders, employed what method of killing royals to prevent the ground from being sullied by royal blood? The rebel Nayan and the Abbasid caliph met this fate.",
        "answer": "rolling into a carpet and being trampled by horses anything involving trampling, really"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "UN Security Council 338 called for an end to this war. The decisive Operation Gazelle altered the course of this war. Fort Budapest was attacked early on in this war, which begun with Operation Badr. The battle of Chinese Farm was fought in order for one side to establish a canal bridgehead in this war. The Agranat Commission noted that Golda Meir was not responsible for being caught off guard in this war, which began with a surprise Syrian attack on the Golan Heights. For ten points, name this 1973 war in which the Arabs struck on the Jewish day of atonement.",
        "answer": "Yom Kippur War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fort Budapest was a part of this defensive line built by the Israelis. It was placed along the edge of the Suez Canal following the War of Attrition, and named for an Israeli chief of staff.",
        "answer": "Bar Lev Line"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the prelude to this legislation’s creation, Warren Atherton asked Francis Sullivan to “gather all the problems.” An amendment to this legislation was offered by Gillespie Montgomery, whose version of it included a monthly $100 payment. Speaking on this legislation, Harry Colmery said “Never again do we want to see the honor and glory of our nation fade to the extent that the men of arms” “totter from door to door.” For ten points, name this bill created in 1944 to aid returning World War II veterans.",
        "answer": [
          "G.I. Bill of Rights",
          "Servicemen’s Readjustment Act of 1944"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The original G.I Bill excluded members of this civilian sailing force, despite its critical role in World War II.",
        "answer": "United States Merchant Marine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this war, one side’s headquarters was destroyed in the Battle of Holy Ground. Benjamin Hawkins failed to adequately prepare for this conflict, in which the Spanish governor armed one side at Pensacola. Peter McQueen and William Weatherford instigated the massacre of Fort Mims in this conflict, which was ended by the Treaty of Fort Jackson. American forces became involved in this war following the Battle of Burnt Corn. For ten points, name this 1814 Native American civil war involving the Red Sticks faction of one of the Five Civilized Tribes.",
        "answer": [
          "Creek War",
          "Red Stick War before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This general helped end the Creek War following a decisive victory at Horseshoe Bend. He had earlier established Forts Detroit and Strother in the Tennessee campaign.",
        "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a bout of mental instability, this leader abdicated in favour of his son Louis I, but retook the throne after Louis’ death less than a year later. Attempts to retake parts of Italy by this ruler’s minister Giulio Alberoni led to his defeat by the War of the Quadruple Alliance. Despite the objections of Archduke Charles of Austria, this ruler ended up succeeding the last Habsburg Charles II. For ten points, name this first Bourbon King of Spain, whose rise to the throne was the subject of the War of Spanish Succession.",
        "answer": "Philip V of Spain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of the Quadruple Alliance was ended by a treaty signed in this city. The Nine Years War was ended by a treaty that was signed nearby at Ryswick.",
        "answer": "The Hague"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A cryptic letter written during this scandal notes “The aspens will already be turning. [...] Come back to work - and life.” In this scandal, classified information was leaked by State Department official Richard Armitage, possibly as retribution for the “What I Didn’t Find in Africa,” op-ed opposing the invasion of Iraq. Lewis “Scooter” Libby was found guilty of obstruction of justice for his role in this scandal, which forced the resignation of its central figure. For ten points, name this 2003 scandal in which the wife of Joseph Wilson was publicly “outed” as a CIA agent.",
        "answer": [
          "Valerie Plame affair",
          "Plamegate",
          "anything that mentions Valerie Plame in any way"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "”What I Didn’t Find in Africa” found that Saddam Hussein did not, in fact, purchase massive amounts of the yellowcake version of what substance in Africa?",
        "answer": "yellowcake uranium"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler refused to convert to Islam because he could not give up alcohol, which he called “the joy of our lives.” This ruler forced Rogneda to marry him during his war with his brother Yaropolk. During the revolt of Bardas Phocas, this man helped Basil the Bulgar-Slayer crush the revolt by sending six thousand experienced soldiers. This man built the Church of the Tithes after his marriage to Byzantine princess Anna, after which a mass baptism in the Dnieper River occurred. For ten points, name this ruler who converted the Kievan Rus to Christianity.",
        "answer": [
          "Vladimir I or Vladimir the Great",
          "or Saint Vladimir",
          "or Vladimir Veliky",
          "or Svyatoy Vladimir",
          "or Vladimir Svyatoslavich"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The six thousand soldiers Vladimir the Great sent to Basil the Bulgar-Slayer eventually formed the core of what Byzantine military unit, who served as the personal bodyguards of the emperor?",
        "answer": "Varangian Guard"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Belgrade’s Red Star Stadium’s nickname was inspired by this venue, which is officially named for a journalist who campaigned for its construction, Mario Filho. This venue is named for the native birds that occupied the location where this stadium was built. In this stadium’s “blow,” Uruguay defeated the host nation 2-1 in the finals of the 1950 World Cup. Germany defeated Argentina in overtime at this sporting venue, which will host both the opening and closing ceremonies for the 2016 Summer Olympics. For ten points, name this site of the finals of the 2014 FIFA World Cup, a large soccer stadium located in Rio de Janeiro.",
        "answer": [
          "Maracan˜a Stadium or Est´adio do Maracan˜a",
          "Est´adio Jornalista Mario Filho before read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Maracan˜azo was considered by Brazilians to be their worst sports defeat ever, until an even more humiliating defeat in the 2014 FIFA World Cup semifinal. Give the outcome of the game in terms of the scores of Brazil and its opponent.",
        "answer": "Germany 7, Brazil 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer’s only cello sonata, written in G minor, was dedicated to Auguste Franchomme. This composer’s Opus 10 and Opus 25 include a G-flat major work with rapid triplets in the right hand, and another written in response to the November Uprising. This composer was the first to use the term “ballade” for instrumental music, likely inspired by the poetry of Adam Mickiewicz. The “Black Key” and “Revolutionary” Etudes were written by, for ten points, what Polish composer of many mazurkas and polonaises?",
        "answer": "Fr´ed´eric Chopin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chopin wrote his preludes on Majorca while having an affair with this person, with whom he is portrayed in a Delacroix double portrait. She used a pseudonym to publish works like Indiana.",
        "answer": "George Sand or Amantine Lucile Aurore Dupin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John of Lancaster, Duke of Bedford, ruled out of this city while serving as regent for Henry VI. The patron saint of this city is said to have picked up his head after being martyred and walked for 6 miles, That man names a suburb of this city, St. Denis. This city’s Faubourg St. Antoine was the site of a building torn down after Bernard de Launay was executed, and its Latin Quarter is home to a namesake university. For ten points, name this city, the site of the Sorbonne and the Bastille.",
        "answer": "Paris"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "St. Denis was killed in this Parisian district, which translates to “Mountain of the Martyr.” The Basilica of the Sacred Heart is also on this large Parisian hill.",
        "answer": "Montmartre"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ALASKA",
      "prompt": "In the history of Alaska, what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "country from which the United States purchased Alaska Territory?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "most populous Alaskan city devastated by the 1964 Good Friday Earthquake?",
          "answer": "Anchorage"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alaskan island chain invaded by the Japanese in World War II?",
          "answer": "Aleutian islands"
        },
        {
          "question": "company whose Valdez tanker spilled oil in Prince William Sound in 1989?",
          "answer": "Exxon"
        },
        {
          "question": "western city where a gold discovery led to the Klondike rush?",
          "answer": "Nome"
        },
        {
          "question": "disease whose 1925 outbreak required serum to be delivered on dog sleds?",
          "answer": "diptheria"
        },
        {
          "question": "northern terminus of the Trans-Alaska Pipeline where oil was found in 1968?",
          "answer": "Prudhoe Bay"
        },
        {
          "question": "capital of Alaska Territory until it moved to Juneau in 1906?",
          "answer": "Sitka"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SPANISH ARCHITECTURE",
      "prompt": "In the historical architecture of Spain, who or what is the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "city home to the 18th-century Royal Palace and current capital?",
          "answer": "Madrid"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catalan city home to Park Guell and unfinished Sagrada Familia?",
          "answer": "Barcelona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish architect who designed that park and church?",
          "answer": "Antoni Gaudi"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York art museum that opened a Bilbao branch designed by Frank Gehry?",
          "answer": "Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum"
        },
        {
          "question": "fortress in Granada home to the Court of the Lions and arabesque details?",
          "answer": "Alhambra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Islamic dynasty of Abd Al-Rahman that built the Great Mosque in C´ordoba?",
          "answer": "Umayyad"
        },
        {
          "question": "city home to the Roman Alcantara Bridge and the Castle of San Servando?",
          "answer": "Toledo"
        },
        {
          "question": "city of the revival-style Plaza de Espan˜a in its Maria Luisa Park?",
          "answer": "Seville"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "VIETNAM",
      "prompt": "In the history of Vietnam, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "northern city that is its current capital?",
          "answer": "Hanoi or Ha Noi"
        },
        {
          "question": "European power that held Vietnam as part of the colony of Indochina?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "independence leader who became the first leader of Communist Vietnam?",
          "answer": "Ho Chi Minh or Nguyen Sinh Cung"
        },
        {
          "question": "colonial capital renamed after that independence leader?",
          "answer": "Saigon"
        },
        {
          "question": "1954 Battle whose victory by Vietnam clinched independence?",
          "answer": "Dien Bien Phu"
        },
        {
          "question": "dynasty that ruled Vietnam from the 19th century until independence and most common Vietnamese surname?",
          "answer": "Nguyen"
        },
        {
          "question": "central city that was capital of that dynasty?",
          "answer": "Hue"
        },
        {
          "question": "pair of first century military leaders who revolted against the Chinese before being defeated by Ma Yuan?",
          "answer": "Trung sisters or Trung Trac and Trung Nhi"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Howard’s End, Helen Schlegel claims this piece represents “goblins marching across the universe.” E.T.A. Hoffman wrote a glowing review of this piece, whose third movement begins similarly to the last movement of Mozart’s (20 pts)",
        "Great G minor symphony. This piece is quoted in every movement of a piano sonata whose movements are named for famous New England authors. William Ives’ (10 pts)",
        "Concord Sonata musically quotes, for ten points, what symphony that opens “G, G, G, E flat,” a motif described as “fate knocking at the door,” that was composed by Ludwig van Beethoven? ANSWER:LudwigvanBeethoven’sSymphonyNo.5inCminor(Beethovennotneededaftermentioned) (2) Critics of American coverage of this war note that the media believed that one side’s soldiers held plastic keys that would grant them instant access to paradise. The USS Stark was hit by two (+) Exocet missiles launched by one side during this conflict. This conflict was ended by UN Resolution 528, which restored pre-war boundaries according to the Algiers Agreement. Operation (*) Scorch Sword was an unsuccessful attempt by one side in this conflict to destroy the other’s Osirak reactor. For ten points, name this 1980-1988 war between two Middle Eastern nations led by Saddam Hussein and Ayatollah Khomeini."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Iran-Iraq War",
        "names in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The perpetrator of this event used a pseudonym based on Star Trek, Robert D. Kling. This event led to the passing of AEDPA. The perpetrator of this event carried an envelope containing pages from the Turner Diaries and cited a passage from John Locke about the right to (20 pts)",
        "kill those who take away liberty. This event was supposedly motivated by the Ruby Ridge incident and Waco siege, and it employed an altered Ryder truck. It was the (10 pts)",
        "deadliest attack on American soil before 9/11. For ten points, name this terrorist attack carried out by Timothy McVeigh the Alfred P. Murrah federal building."
      ],
      "answer": "Oklahoma City bombing"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Henry Graham regarded it his “sad duty” that he and Nicholas Katzenbach were ordered to break up this event. The man who performed this event had earlier “[tossed] the gauntlet before the feet of tyranny” in a speech supporting this event’s goal. Unexpectedly, (20 pts)",
        "Dave McGlathery did not arrive at the Foster Auditorium to attend this event, which opposed the actions of Vivian Malone and James Hood. John F. Kennedy ordered the (10 pts)",
        "National Guard to stop this event, whose perpetrator had promised “segregation today, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever”. For ten points, name this June 11, 1963 act of opposition to the integration of the University of Alabama, in which George Wallace literally obstructed a civil right."
      ],
      "answer": "Stand in the Schoolhouse Door propmt on descriptions of George Wallace preventing the integration of the University of Alabama before “University” is read"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a letter to his wife, Walter Congreve stated he did not participate in this event as he “thought they might not be able to resist a general.” On the 100th anniversary of this event, members of the Royal Welch Fusiliers recreated a (20 pts)",
        "soccer game at a Frelinghien monument. Pope Benedict XV advocated for an official version of this event by asking “that the guns may fall (10 pts)",
        "silent, at least upon the night the angels sang.” A photo of this event shows British and German Soldiers standing arm-in-arm between opposing trenches. For ten points, name this very brief lull in World War I that took place in December 1914."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "World War I Christmas Truce",
        "descriptions of soldiers not fighting on Christmas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One monument to this battle was the finish line for the marathon at the 1960 Summer Olympics. This battle was preceded by clashes at Turin and Verona, where Ruricius Pompeianus was killed. The loser of this battle misinterpreted the statement of the (20 pts)",
        "Sibylline books that “an enemy of Rome would perish.” It took place at an endpoint of the Via Flaminia. The winner used a military standard, the Labarum, supposedly after (10 pts)",
        "seeing a vision of a cross with the words “in hoc signo vinces” in the sky. That winner later converted to Christianity. For ten points, name this battle in which Maxentius was defeated by Constantine near a structure spanning the Tiber River."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Milvian Bridge"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One writer from this country who was stabbed to death by a mentally deranged man wrote the poetry collection Alma America. One writer from this country called Mexico a “perfect dictatorship,” and wrote a novel in which a writer at (20 pts)",
        "Radio Panamericana has an affair with an older woman. A novel set in this country ends with the burning at the stake of Brother Juniper, who had earlier witnessed a rope bridge collapse. The books (10 pts)",
        "Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter and The Bridge of San Luis Rey are set in, for ten points, what home country of writer Mario Vargas Llosa that inspired Pablo Neruda’s poem “The Heights of Macchu Picchu?”"
      ],
      "answer": "Peru"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Stanley Stein founded The Star to raise awareness about these people, while living in a place established for these people in Carville, Louisiana. The House is Black is a film about a village of these people in Iran, founded by Farah Pahlavi at Behkadeh Raji. King (20 pts)",
        "Baldwin IV of Jerusalem was one of these people, who lived in Kalawao County, overseen by the Board of Health, during the reign of Kamehameha V. Father (10 pts)",
        "Damien served in a colony on Molokai that hosted, for ten points, what sufferers of a chronic infection by a mycobaceterium, otherwise known as Hansen’s Disease, who suffer from skin lesions?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "lepers",
        "people who suffer from leprosy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Wall Street Journal called this case “The Decision Everyone Won.” Archibald Cox’s oral argument in this case noted that he was a Harvard graduate. This case was instigated when a white (20 pts)",
        "medical school applicant was rejected from the medical school at Davis, though his scores were higher than some minorities who applied. Lewis Powell wrote this case’s opinion, which was affirmed in (10 pts)",
        "Grutter v. Bollinger. For ten points, name this 1978 Supreme Court case that upheld affirmative action, but ruled that racial quotas in university admissions were unconstitutional."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Regents of the University of California v. Bakke",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Zakerzonia colloquially referred to the area west of this line. A 1919-1921 war over disputes over this line was ended by the Peace of Riga, which gave one country almost 200 kilometers of land east of this line. At the (20 pts)",
        "Yalta Conference, this line was formalized as one country’s eastern border. This line was crossed from the east on September 17, (10 pts)",
        "1939 per the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact by the Red Army. For ten points, name this line demarcating the border between Poland and Russia, named after the Viceroy of India who drew it."
      ],
      "answer": "Curzon Line"
    }
  ]
}